<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-08-16T20:21:12+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">eddymikes.me</title><subtitle>Personal blog</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Quitter!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/08/07/quitter.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Quitter!" /><published>2022-08-07T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-08-07T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/08/07/quitter</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/08/07/quitter.html">&lt;p&gt;I just quit my job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How’s that for a hook? No, it wasn’t as rash of a decision as that one-liner makes it seem. It’s actually something I’ve been ruminating on for a while, with increasing intensity over the past 18-24 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I’m at an “inflection” or transition point in my career. Having worked in finance since I graduated college in 2013, it only dawned on me two or so years ago that I’ve been on a journey away from finance and towards entrepreneurship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So where did it all begin?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got into investment banking out of college for a few reasons. I don’t know if they were the right ones, they probably weren’t:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I wanted to learn a lot (about anything, just a lot)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I wanted to “credentialize” my CV&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Money&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My friends were doing it, and I identified with the culture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three out of these four reasons revolve around one theme: preserving optionality. Knowing nothing about finance and having no idea what I wanted to do in life, that rationale seemed somewhat sensible, so I dove in. Almost a decade later, it’s clear to me that I was wearing major blinders that prevented me from being intellectually honest about who I am, where my true interests lie, and what I (maybe) should be doing with my life… stubbornly “preserving optionality” at all costs without thinking critically about these things. I can chalk it up to immaturity, lack of experience, or plain old not knowing until I know, but here we are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back on the last 9 years moving through roles in various sub-sectors of finance, two things occurred to me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I was never organically super excited about what I was doing.&lt;/strong&gt; Every manifesto ever written will tell you requirement #1 for being happy and successful in life is to love what you do. Ask anyone who knows me - I am an &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; enthusiastic person by nature. This never came through in my work. Big red flag🚩&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My absolutely highest performing state when I was out of a job and out there hustling&lt;/strong&gt; to get hired by companies that felt out of my reach (in one case after already having quit my job). My sheer levels of cognition and drive were on another level. I’ve started a handful of side hustles and projects over the last 24 months and noticed the exact same thing. Something about the lack of a salary safety net combined with pure organic interest unlocked something within me. This isn’t all that surprising, but sometimes it just hits home after the fact.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Realizing these two things ignited some serious introspection. Why was I really spending my time this way, swinging through the jungles of finance with tunnel vision? How can I better spend my time to maximize my happiness and potential?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being honest with myself, the answer to the first question came pretty easily: I was working my way through finance because it was the lucrative thing to do. The safe thing to do. The thing to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s safe to say that’s not a great way to go through life if one can help it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second question, however, took me deeper down the introspection rabbit hole. What am I good at? What do I even like? What the heck do I even want in life?!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two years of exploring what I think I want in life can be distilled down to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Freedom.&lt;/strong&gt; Not being a slave to my job. Living the lifestyle I want. Living in a state of pure meritocracy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The ability to travel, live a comfortable healthy life, and have a big family.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do something impactful.&lt;/strong&gt; Having some sort of direct positive impact on other people or the world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that’s what I want, but what am I good at? More importantly, what am I good at that is relatively unqiue?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an effort to prevent this post from becoming one big pat on the back, I’ll leave it here: I energize others, I can &lt;a href=&quot;http://paulgraham.com/schlep.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;schlep&lt;/a&gt; like the best of them, and I’m decisive (I can “pull trig”, for better or worse).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, so all of that is true, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; I have the most fun and perform at my highest level when working and setting higher stakes for myself?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;🚨Revelation Alert🚨&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I need to merge my strengths with my desires.&lt;/strong&gt; These observations about my past and conclusions about my future led me straight to entrepreneurship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve toyed with many ideas for starting my own business since middle school, but never moved forward with anything along the way, which is a bit strange since I was a little &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; comfortable with risk in my formative years. The desire was always there, but it’s clear to me now that I was ignoring it for all the wrong reasons. It feels like I was under the influence of the blue pill!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add on the fact that working for a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paulgraham.com/boss.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;corporate boss&lt;/a&gt; (save for the few amazing ones I’ve had) grates excruciatingly against every fiber of my being, my recent “red pill revelations” are causing every bone in my body to scream: “Do it!” “Jump!” “Go for it!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Said differently, all this fancy introspection can probably be reduced down to a good old entrepreneurial itch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some itches must be scratched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m currently working on a startup in Hong Kong, but even if I didn’t think this project was worth working on, I’d quit my job anyway. I genuinely believe I have the ability to “figure it out” and “make shit happen”, and it’s worth noting that I’m pretty incapable of delivering the required level of focus when my peak mental hours are consumed by a day job. Sitting at a job is anything but positioning myself to get lucky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We shall see. It’s not all exciting and glamorous. The highs of achieving what you want are high, but the lows of the pursuit are very low. Going off to sustain myself on my own and pursue what I want in life is likely to be far more challenging than anything I’ve done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BUT… People tend to overestimate risk, and sometimes you gotta burn the boats and bet on yourself! Away we go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;thanks-text&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks to Sarah for reading a draft of this post.
&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Jump!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why I started this blog</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/08/06/why-i-started-this-blog.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why I started this blog" /><published>2022-08-06T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-08-06T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/08/06/why-i-started-this-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/08/06/why-i-started-this-blog.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been thinking about starting a blog for a while, but here I am sitting at Hong Kong International Airport with two hours until my flight to New York, and something just came over me, so I started typing away. Here goes nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started this blog for three reasons: &lt;strong&gt;1) clear writing = clear thinking, 2) exploring unknown unknowns, and 3) accountability.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;clear-writing--clear-thinking&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clear writing = clear thinking&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spend the vast majority of my intellectually demanding time consuming information and content, rather than producing/creating it. Books, podcasts, blogs, articles, my Twitter feed, YouTube videos… it’s pretty much a one way street of information input.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All that information represents some of the building blocks of the ideas I have and views I form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Translating ideas from thoughts in one’s head into comprehendible written words challenges one to more deeply understand what they think. It’s amazing how I’ll think I know something and try to write it out, and that exercise reveals how hollow that thinking can actually be sometimes. There are other areas of life where I’m writing - occasionally at my day job, for startups/side projects I’ve worked on, job hunts, etc., but it’s pretty infrequent. Forcing myself to write more stimulates a another part of my brain, reinforces and challenges my ideas, and improves the depth and quality of my thinking (if I was on the fence about that before, writing this first post proves it to me.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog is a pursuit of clearer, deeper thinking about the things that interest me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a rough idea of what I plan to write about (entrepreneurship/business, health &amp;amp; fitness, learning, productivity, travel/living abroad, anything else I come to be interested in), but I’m excited to see where this goes. Which brings me to my next reason…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;exploring-unknown-unknowns&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exploring unknown unknowns&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideas beget ideas. I don’t understand the brain chemistry behind this, they just do. I don’t know what I’ll uncover about myself or what ideas will occur to me by challenging myself to write more, but I know I’ll uncover something. It would be cool to see what that’s all about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;accountability&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accountability&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could just write in a journal, but there’s something about the act of posting something online for the world to see. We’re not talking about high stakes here, but it does hold me to a higher standard. The internet is &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;forever&lt;/a&gt;, so there’s an incentive to really think through what I’m writing about. This ties into clear writing = clear thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those are the main reasons, but this is also another fun coding challenge! I’m picking up programming on the side (I’ll probably write about that), and a personal blog or website is a great early practical application of that skillset. This blog is completely self-developed and hosted using GitHub Pages, Jekyll, basic HTML/CSS, and Namecheap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an aside, despite having read it for some time, I only just noticed that a high school friend of mine has been running his &lt;a href=&quot;https://blas.com/essays/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;awesome blog&lt;/a&gt; for what appears to be the exact same reasons! One inspiration point to you, my friend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-in-a-name&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What’s in a name?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“E Mikes”, “Eddy Mikes” or many variations thereof was given to me as a nickname in high school, and it’s stuck ever since. Keepin’ it rolling!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
And BOOM! First blog post complete. Stay tuned for more, I hope you enjoy reading!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;thanks-text&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks to Sarah for reading a draft of this post.
&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Brain stuff</summary></entry></feed>