<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-11-24T14:38:33+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">eddymikes.me</title><subtitle>Personal blog</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Only Way Out is Through</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/11/24/the-only-way-out-is-through.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Only Way Out is Through" /><published>2023-11-24T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2023-11-24T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/11/24/the-only-way-out-is-through</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/11/24/the-only-way-out-is-through.html">&lt;p&gt;It’s been nearly a year since I &lt;a href=&quot;https://eddymikes.me/2022/08/07/quitter.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;quit my job&lt;/a&gt; to be an “entrepreneur”, and would ya look at that, the Imposter Syndrome is really starting to sink in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I quit my day job because I doubted my ability to deliver if my attention was being split between work and side projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In classic whack-a-mole fashion, solving that problem introduced another… cash flow. Surprise!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew I was sacrificing cash flow in the near term, but I underestimated how little &lt;em&gt;visibility&lt;/em&gt; I would have into when things would stabilize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My current venture, Chowtime, is struggling, and we might have to shut it down. Even if Chowtime had a more compelling path forward, predicting when I could draw even a small salary would be difficult. How much and how fast we grow, the cost of that growth, fundraising size and structure… there are just too many variables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As time marches on, my financial runway increasingly feels like a gun in my hand, loaded with bullets called time and money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those bullets are finite, and I fire one when I pursue a new project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can reload the gun, sure, but that usually requires firing the gun too (spending money to make money).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I fired a bullet when I started Chowtime, and given its outlook, I’m starting to explore other ways to generate income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The combination of passing time and a fixed number of bullets is putting a lot of pressure on me to not miss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;main-section&quot;&gt;What’s the buy in?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One obvious way to minimize this risk is to choose big targets. Promising opportunities. Good businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Astute observation, genius!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That shouldn’t be a problem for me, I’m smart, hungry, and disciplined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh wait, 99% of successful entrepreneurs (more on that definition later) have these things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These qualities are, quite literally, table stakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;blue-box&quot;&gt;A quick detour on the definition of “table stakes”:
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Walk up to a black jack table and the buy in is $100? $100 is that table’s stakes. You need $100 just to take a seat. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;So you have $100? Good for you! Now take a seat and start competing against everyone at the table, all of whom, wait for it… &lt;strong&gt;also have $100&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s become clear to me that the traits I was putting a lot of stock in to be successful are just the entry tickets to play the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I lack is experience and honed judgement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, I have a decade of experience in finance and my own instincts, but that is not directly transferable to starting your own business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The finance experience helps with understanding how businesses work, but does almost nothing for execution and opportunity selection, the real needle movers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to become good at golf, you don’t watch golf videos, you golf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Judgement and experience can only be acquired through doing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;main-section&quot;&gt;You are now entering the Spiral of Self Doubt&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the entrepreneurship space, I’m a freshmen, a rookie, a n00b.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve learned a ton launching and growing Chowtime, but it’s hard to shake the feeling that I’m just scrambling around in the dark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anxiety-inducing to say the least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m trying to minimize the risk of wasting one of those precious bullets by shining as much light on the landscape as possible. Reading, networking, observing trends, etc., and yet…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;u&gt;The uncomfortable reality&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;strong&gt;The most effective way to shine that light is by firing those very bullets.&lt;/strong&gt; By doing stuff. By taking risk. By starting businesses. By firing and probably missing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I knew entrepreneurship and risk-taking are one in the same when I made the leap. But facing the reality of risk while you have a salary-paying job and while you’re going it alone are two very different things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things become more “real” than ever before. Especially the reality that failing is a serious possibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All sorts of crazy emotions start erupting under these circumstances, predominantly a shift from self-confidence to self-doubt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This &lt;em&gt;Spiral of Self Doubt&lt;/em&gt; creeps in gradually. It starts with a slight lack of motivation before morphing into a feeling of foolishness. I start to feel a silly and sometimes have trouble taking myself seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two conflicting voices emerge in my head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Voice #1:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“This is stupid. You are stupid. This is a cute, silly joke. See you at your job in five years after making no money.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Voice #2:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The only way to get there is to start. It may not work, but the perfect idea will never just appear, you must go to it. It’s part of the process. Just start.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Voice #2 is a nice thing, but I wish I could say it’s louder than Voice #1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It isn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Voice #1 usually prevails, and when it does, I fall into a anxiety-inducing, judgement-clouding loop:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Spiral of Self Doubt makes me anxious, which makes me worried about my judgement being clouded, which crushes my self-confidence, which makes me more anxious, and so on.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that, ladies and gentlemen, is was we call Imposter Syndrome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;main-section&quot;&gt;How I’m dealing with it&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pretty grim, huh?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes and no.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spiraling into anxiety and Imposter Syndrome is painful, but it’s also a powerful catalyst for action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, execution is all that really matters, and nothing undermines execution like Imposter Syndrome. If I let it win, my chances of success dwindle to zero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, the harsh reality of Imposter Syndrome is what motivates me to overcome it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Imposter is beatable. Here’s how:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;By setting an attainable goal&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to what defines a “successful entrepreneur”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a spectrum of success. On one end you have the likes of Mr. Bezos. We can all imagine what that looks like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other end you have the bare minimum necessary for self-sustainability. Expense coverage, modest wealth accumulation, freedom to do what you want with a low burn lifestyle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s my goal. To provide for myself and my family through my own sustainable cash flow businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It requires dedication, but it’s a low(ish) bar and is very achievable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, I can &lt;em&gt;visualize&lt;/em&gt; achieving it. It doesn’t seem unrealistic if I look in the mirror and am completely honest with myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having an attainable North Star makes the beast of entrepreneurship a lot less intimidating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;By getting a mentor&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This dawned on me one day as a complete no-brainer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m at the bottom of the ocean, and it seems obvious to get the advice of someone who’s already made it to the surface. A successful entrepreneur. Someone who has done this. Tried and failed. Tried and succeeded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s no reason to make things harder than they need to be. Entrepreneurship is hard enough as it is, and I’m a firm believer in getting all the help one can get.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is absolutely something I’m willing to pay for, and I’ve started preparing a list of entrepreneurs to reach out to. Eventually, someone will take my call, and it will be worth every penny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Would you try to get good at tennis without getting a coach?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;By getting a therapist&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another obvious one. I resisted for a while, but the benefits of just talking things out with a neutral party are huge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t always work, but having a roughly once per month cadence with my therapist has been good for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re feeling particularly crippled by anxiety, give it a shot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;By remembering that I learn concretely by doing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember those kids in school who seemed to pick up subjects with ease just by studying a bit, acing every test?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was not me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned what I had to by studying hard and grinding. And I got by with reasonably good grades, nothing special.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When forced to learn something on someone else’s time that I don’t truly care about (school, professional projects at jobs I wasn’t passionate about), that’s what happens, I get by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learn and deliver, but mainly because I have to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when I pursue something I’m deeply energized by and have the time to try and fail on my own time, the quality of learning and skill acquisition is MUCH higher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retention, depth &amp;amp; breadth of understanding, my ability to generate ideas based on what I’ve learned… All of it feels super charged. I feel like a true outperformer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put simply, I have the ability to get really good at certain things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This gives me faith that though it may not feel like it today, I have it in me to become a very capable entrepreneur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;By remembering that I enjoy the journey&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imposter Syndrome can shatter confidence, but there are a few things I’m still deeply confident in:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My love of learning new things, building stuff, and pursuing goals.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The compounding effect of my day-to-day effort, even if it sometimes feels like I’m going nowhere or even backward.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a bit cliche, admittedly, but reminding myself is an effective way to maintain focus and keep my anxiety at bay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Results matter, but it’s not just about the end game. The joy is in the pursuit itself, the struggle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever the I feel the Spiral coming on, I try to remember that &lt;strong&gt;Imposter Syndrome is part of the journey&lt;/strong&gt; and a natural result of the path I’ve chosen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self-confidence will return, and Imposter Syndrome will be back again too. It’s part of the ride, and I’m sure as hell not getting off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way out is through 💪&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;thanks-text&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks to Sarah for reading a draft of this post.
&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Thoughts from an Imposter (Syndrome)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Man learns to code at tender age of 31</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/05/04/man-learns-to-code-at-tender-age-of-31.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Man learns to code at tender age of 31" /><published>2023-05-04T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2023-05-04T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/05/04/man-learns-to-code-at-tender-age-of-31</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/05/04/man-learns-to-code-at-tender-age-of-31.html">&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;In this article:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-why&quot;&gt;The Why&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-how&quot;&gt;The How&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#reflections&quot;&gt;Reflections&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My hand trembled with anticipation as it hovered over the enter key. Six weeks of hard work had led to this moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sickened by months of manual Excel work, I had finally cobbled together a bloated code file that &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; be smart enough to do all of that mind-numbing work for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emerging from hundreds of lines of code and countless squashed bugs, I found myself playing chicken with the enter key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d come too far to back down, too far to cower back into the depths of manual data crunching. There was only one thing left to do:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Smash that enter key and hope for the best.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was fairly sure this would work. But if I was wrong, back to code review hell I’d go to comb through my monstrosity in hope of finding and fixing yet another error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here goes nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…&lt;em&gt;cocks gun noise&lt;/em&gt;… &lt;strong&gt;ENTER&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a split second of utter stillness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, the terminal sprang to life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Progress statements ran down the screen like rapid fire, making me feel like a bona fide NSA hacker. Pretty baller.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About three seconds later, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;done&lt;/code&gt; printed to the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stillness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The moment of truth was upon me. Did two hours of my life just collapse into three seconds?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All I had to do was open one Excel file to find out…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the story of how I &lt;s&gt;learned&lt;/s&gt; &lt;em&gt;am learning&lt;/em&gt; how to code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much like starting a blog, learning to code has long lingered in the back of my mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finally pulled the trigger in earnest in late 2021, and one game of chicken with my enter key has left me more energized than ever almost two years later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe this post will serve as inspiration to some of you who have been thinking about programming, but just need a little nudge to get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;thanks-text&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Quick note on the title of this post: It always amazes me how often people don’t try something new because they’re “too old”. Life expectancies are rising, people. It’s never too late to start.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;main-section&quot;&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;the-why&quot;&gt;The Why&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finally pulled the trigger for several reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I wanted to throw rocket fuel on my creative fire.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I wanted to challenge my 🧠.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I wanted to automate work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;Creativity &amp;amp; Entrepreneurship&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a recently &lt;a href=&quot;https://eddymikes.me/2022/08/07/quitter.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;self-proclaimed wantrepreneur&lt;/a&gt;, I’ve quickly learned that entrepreneurship is difficult. Really difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ability to keep stepping up to the plate is critical to success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no shortage of ideas that do not require software, but if I’m able to take on problems that can be solved with even the simplest technology-based* products, the universe of ideas explodes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Programming skills at the prototyping level will put the raw power of creation my hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;thanks-text&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;*Note: “Technology-based”, for the purposes of this post, means any business where the product or service is software, or where the core value proposition is driven or enabled by software.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;Problem solving&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Programming is very intellectually demanding and, at its core, is about problem solving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a way to push myself intellectually and become a better problem solver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Programming is especially appealing because progress is not dependent on anyone or anything. I don’t need a teacher to schedule time with, waves to surf, or a team to play against. All the resources to learn are freely available, and I don’t need anyone’s permission to start writing code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All I need is a computer and an internet connection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;Automating work&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having started my career in investment banking, I became quite the little Excel monkey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An unintended side effect of my unnecessary level of Excel mastery was massive impatience for manual work and things taking longer than they should.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like absurd impatience. Like &lt;em&gt;“relax bro, you’re weirdly too impatient about this”&lt;/em&gt; impatience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not really an issue when the entire job consisted of pumping out simple spreadsheets and charts for PowerPoint presentations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But years later, when I found myself at a job that required much more manual data crunching than I was accustomed to, that impatience began to rear its ugly head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To pile it on, my company had a large technology department, so I was constantly forced to watch in a potent cocktail of awe and agony as my developer colleagues automated away their manual work. All while I bitterly trudged through mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spend enough time watching other people do something in a fraction of the time it takes you, and well…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Impatient guy sees better way to get things done, decides to learn how.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;main-section&quot;&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;the-how&quot;&gt;Projects, baby! Projects!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With most things, the most effective way to learn is through practical application. In programming land, that means building stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What kind of stuff? Whatever floats your boat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve found the best projects a) pique your interest and/or b) can be implemented immediately with your current skillset or after learning a bite-sized amount of something new.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means start small.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;Project 1: Employ the robots&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember the heart-pounding opener to this post? Enter &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Python_(programming_language)&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Python is a popular programming language for automating Excel work and is the golden child in finance. Naturally, learning enough to automate some of my manual misery became my first bogie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used &lt;a href=&quot;http://automatetheboringstuff.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;automatetheboringstuff.com&lt;/a&gt; and was up and running with live Python scripts inside six weeks. These scripts migrated the responsibility of managing several manual processes from me…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…to my computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know, I know. The suspense has been killing you. How did that game of chicken with my enter key play out?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did indeed check that Excel file, and by what feels like some miracle, my enter key lost!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two hours of my life did, in fact, collapse into &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;three seconds&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cannot understate how good this feels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the course of a few weeks, I automated several daily and monthly manual processes that previously consumed about eight hours of my time each month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Approximately ninety hours of upfront investment (three hours of coding/day, five days/week, for about six weeks) to save eight hours of work per month. Payback in one year, and I’ve picked up a new skill that I can use forever. Seems like a good trade to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;Project 2: Roast the fellas&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My friends and I use &lt;a href=&quot;https://groupme.com/en-US/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Groupme&lt;/a&gt; as our chat group. Luck would have it that Groupme has an open &lt;a href=&quot;https://dev.groupme.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;API&lt;/a&gt;, giving the programmatically inclined access to all of their own personal messaging data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My group chat has been in use for seven years, averaging 30 messages per day…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…methinks a closer look at the data is in order 🤔.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter my next project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used Python to gather our group chat’s entire messaging history from Groupme’s API, slice and dice it, and put it into a silly but illuminating presentation for the boys. The result was a twenty page deck pumped full of cute stats on my friends’ proclivity to absolutely roast each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They liked it, to say the least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a little taste of what is now an annual production:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/groupme-presentation-slide.png&quot; alt=&quot;groupme-presentation-slide&quot; title=&quot;groupme-presentation-slide&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project only required a minor extension of my Python knowledge into a few &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandas.pydata.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;new&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://pypi.org/project/requests/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;libraries&lt;/a&gt;* and functionalities that are handy for working with large datasets and APIs, and it was a logical next step following my Excel automation work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Success working with Groupme’s simple API inspired me to see what other laughs I could generate at my friends’ expense…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;thanks-text&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;*Note: A library is just a set of pre-written code that you can leverage to get common stuff done instead of reinventing the wheel.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;Project 3: Roast one particular fella&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, Groupme also offers chatbot functionality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if I created a bot in our chat group that singled out one friend of the chattier variety and programmatically roasted him every time he opened his digital mouth?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;width:100%;height:0;padding-bottom:55%;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://giphy.com/embed/26BRBKqUiq586bRVm&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;position:absolute&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;giphy-embed&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://giphy.com/gifs/americasgottalent-agt-americas-got-talent-26BRBKqUiq586bRVm&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And off I went.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used Python and learned just enough &lt;a href=&quot;https://flask.palletsprojects.com/en/2.2.x/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Flask&lt;/a&gt;* to build and host a simple Groupme chatbot app that publicly roasted my friend with one of several snappy comebacks every time he sent a message over a certain length.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funny, it was. Pleased, he was not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;blue-box&quot;&gt;These projects have two important traits that are worth harping upon for a moment. They &lt;strong&gt;1) brought me joy once completed and 2) brought me absolutely nothing until they were completed&lt;/strong&gt;. Said differently, I was working toward something I wanted, and I didn’t get what I wanted until I saw it through to the end. It kept me motivated. Something to think about if you decide to pick up coding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good progress so far, but at this point, I’m but a humble noob. These little projects were fun and undeniably advanced my Python skills, but my ultimate goal is to prototype web-based software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;thanks-text&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;*Note: Flask is a web framework for Python. Similar to a library, a framework is bunch of pre-written code that helps you build web-based apps quickly, from as simple as a Groupme bot to the much more complex.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;Project 4: You’re reading it&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to start with an easy first website project, and I wanted to start writing more for aforementioned &lt;a href=&quot;https://eddymikes.me/2022/08/06/why-i-started-this-blog.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;reasons&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…incoming message from Captain Obvious…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dear Ed,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You should build and launch your own blog.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You’re welcome,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Captain Obvious&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A blog it is then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The blog you’re currently reading was surprisingly easy to get up and running and involved the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Picked a domain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sketched out a simple design&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learned just enough &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTML&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;HTML&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/CSS&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;CSS&lt;/a&gt; (see the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theodinproject.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Odin Project&lt;/a&gt; below)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learned just enough &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; (a popular blog site generator)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Built the site using HTML, CSS, and Jekyll&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hooked up my domain to &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Github Pages&lt;/a&gt;, and hosted the site&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Started writing (hardest part)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a great project because it hit all of my criteria:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;no-bullet-list&quot;&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;✅ Piqued my interest&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;✅ Required me to reach slightly beyond my grasp&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;✅ Generated zero payoff until completed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole exercise took about six weeks. Not bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;What’s next?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a solid understanding of the fundamentals in place, I felt comfortable advancing to the next level of difficulty. To do anything remotely advanced on a website, another programming language is required: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JavaScript&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;JavaScript&lt;/a&gt;, the third core technology of the internet. It makes things come alive on a webpage and is a critical component of all web applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, my programming journey thus far can be summarized as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Python → HTML → CSS → JavaScript&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve learned a tremendous amount, but the material I have yet to cover is immense. The plan is to stay on theme and take on projects that hit all of my criteria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have an app idea in mind. It’s a daunting project, but it will act as a guiding North Star as I navigate the never ending universe of programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;thanks-text&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: All of the above probably seems like a lot, and it is. Programming is a huge time commitment. But I&apos;m not programming every single day. It ebbs and flows with my work load. There have been month-plus long periods where I haven’t been able to think about coding. No deadlines. Learning is a lifelong journey.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;main-section&quot;&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;reflections&quot;&gt;Reflections&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that’s where I’ve been, how I got there, and where I’m going. Here are the big things that come to mind when reflecting on my journey so far. Worth considering before you decide to take it on!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;Programming is satisfying&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Code gives you the power to sit in front of your computer and create something useful in the real world, no welding skills required. If you can dream it up, you can probably build it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That power of creation in your fingertips is intoxicating. The more you learn, the more enjoyable the process of learning becomes, and the faster the idea flywheel spins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;Programming is difficult, frustrating, and time consuming…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make no mistake, programming is not easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is largely because it’s completely digital and pretty abstract. Also, the scope and complexity of material necessary to be dangerous as a programmer is massive. It takes a long time and a lot of effort learning seemingly rudimentary concepts just to get to the beginner level. I’d venture to guess this is a common reason people don’t even start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expect to get stuck on things constantly, sometimes for days or weeks at a time, feeling like you’re making no progress (in reality though, you’re learning).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ability to succeed is highly dependent on one’s ability to stay motivated when it gets dark. This is why your reasons for learning to program and whether it naturally energizes you are so important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s much more to why and how programming is difficult, which you can read about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thinkful.com/blog/why-learning-to-code-is-so-damn-hard/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;…but not as hard as people tend to assume&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having said all that, putting one foot in front of the other will get you there, and at least through the intermediate level, it’s mostly a matter of dedication and consistency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of programming’s difficulty can be overcome by the simple act of chipping away at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s nothing holding you back. It’s just you, your computer, and your desire to learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;main-section&quot;&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Free resources I used to get going fast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve explored &lt;strong&gt;a lot&lt;/strong&gt; of coding content. If you do decide to jump into programming, I recommend checking out these resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://automatetheboringstuff.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Automatetheboringstuff.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cannot recommend this highly enough for beginners. It is an EXCELLENT starting place for learning Python.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing but a free online textbook that explains concepts well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s worth reiterating the point about my game of chicken: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;from nothing, I was up and running with value-adding scripts in six weeks using this resource alone.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Python is a great starting language because it’s modern, intuitive, and widely used with endless resources and community support. It’s also a very powerful language that can do a whole universe of things beyond automating some of your busy work, including build very scalable web applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if you aren’t particularly interested in learning Python but want to learn to build web apps, an equally good place to start is The Odin Project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theodinproject.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Odin Project&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to learn web development as a beginner, The Odin Project is the 🐐. Full stop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The creators assume you have zero programming knowledge and take you through everything you need to know to build a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.geeksforgeeks.org/what-is-full-stack-development/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;full stack&lt;/a&gt; web application from square one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means it is an extremely comprehensive resource that requires months of investment to understand and complete (I still have a ways to go).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having said that, you start seeing results almost immediately. The speed at which I was able to spin up some basic, but decent-looking websites was shocking (here’s a &lt;a href=&quot;https://emikes919-battleship.netlify.app/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;fun one&lt;/a&gt;). You are constantly building a portfolio of work as you advance which serves as a nice reward and motivation to keep going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They give you just enough to keep you going while still forcing you to struggle a bit and figure out a lot on your own (a huge part of programming).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yes, it’s free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;YouTube&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think enough people realize what a goldmine of knowledge exists on YouTube.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to learn it, there’s someone on YouTube waiting to explain it to you like you’re a small child. Over and over again to your little heart’s content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is especially true for programming. YouTube videos have been the sole reason I’ve gotten “unstuck” on many occasions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some favorite channels I’ve used include &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/@funfunfunction&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Fun Fun Function&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/@WesBos&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wes Bos&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/@KevinPowell&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Kevin Powell&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/@WebDevSimplified&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Web Dev Simplified&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;Google&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone who picks up coding will come to find that 90% of your time is spent on Google, not in your code editor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a beginner, there is a 100% chance that whatever problem you’re facing has been solved before. Google will take you to the solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That solution usually exists on &lt;a href=&quot;https://stackoverflow.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;stackoverflow.com&lt;/a&gt;, the Mecca of coding discourse, but can also be found on a long list of great programming websites and forums that Google will find for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of becoming good at programming is a function of how good you become at Googling stuff. The specifics of what you search for can result in huge differences in the time spent solving your problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;My Fiancée&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sarah is a self-taught former integrations engineer and now product manager, having cut her teeth on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Java_(programming_language)&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Java&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://nodejs.org/en&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Node.js&lt;/a&gt;, and Python. She is an absolute machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having her around to graciously get me “unstuck” countless times has really sped things up. I question the judgement of anyone who wouldn’t hire her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, this is a huge leg up on anyone learning to code in a vacuum, but hey, I’ll take it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;⚠️ Avoid: Codecademy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those seriously contemplating the programming journey will have no doubt stumbled upon &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.codecademy.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Codecademy.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I must recommend against it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Set aside that fact that it isn’t free (I have used the paid version), it falls short in one critical area: &lt;strong&gt;Codecademy forces you to write code in their online environment which is not transferable to the real world.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As frustrating as it can be, the payoff of struggling to figure out the day one fundamentals on your own computer is huge. I think Codecademy robs students of this opportunity to “figure it out”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You aren’t required to do any of the dirty work of installing various dependency software and navigating the underbelly of your operating system that’s required at every level of programming in the real world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand why this may be appealing to some people, but I believe it is a sub-optimal way to learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And voilà. Now you know how one game of chicken with my enter key led to an eighteen month (and counting) hobby. Those months feel like years when I think about the ground I’ve covered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, it’s a little scary to re-anchor my perspective back to how much of a beginner I still am and to think about what I’ll have to conquer to get where I want to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A long road ahead, indeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking down that road may be intimidating, but that fear seems nonexistent next to how excited I am to walk down it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that, dear reader, is a good sign if I’ve ever seen one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;thanks-text&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks to Sarah and Julian for reading a draft of this post.
&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">(or how I turned two hours into three seconds)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022 year in review</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/01/26/2022-year-in-review.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022 year in review" /><published>2023-01-26T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2023-01-26T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/01/26/2022-year-in-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/01/26/2022-year-in-review.html">&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;In this article:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#what-happened-in-2022&quot;&gt;What happened in 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#2022-goal-review&quot;&gt;2022 goal review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#learning-through-experience&quot;&gt;Learning through experience in 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#best-books&quot;&gt;Best books I read in 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#2023-goal-setting&quot;&gt;2023 goal setting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#cool-thing&quot;&gt;A cool thing I discovered&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;main-section&quot;&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;what-happened-in-2022&quot;&gt;What happened in 2022?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting year to say the least. On the surface, it looked like an amazing year, but under the hood, it was a rollercoaster of highs and lows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Let’s start with a list, here’s what went down in 2022 (in no particular order):&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quit my job&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Launched a software startup&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tried the keto diet&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Launched this blog&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Coded up a storm&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Got super depressed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Started going to therapy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Injured my leg&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Started putting down books&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Got COVID&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Visited 4 new countries, and Paris for the first time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Went to my first Indian wedding&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Got a Turkish bath&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ran with the bulls in Pamplona, Spain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sheesh! Highs and lows indeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2022 was a year of major transition for me as I &lt;a href=&quot;https://eddymikes.me/2022/08/07/quitter.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;quit my job&lt;/a&gt; and embarked on the path of entrepreneurship. Likely inspired my newly acquired “free agent” status, I conducted my first personal annual review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exercise was motivating, clarifying, and stress-reducing. It brought closure to 2022, helped me recompile what I learned, and gave me a firm handle on how I want to navigate 2023.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.justinwelsh.me/blog/setting-anti-goals&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;a&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sahilbloom.com/newsletter/the-personal-annual-review&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;few&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://tim.blog/2021/12/27/past-year-review/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;resources&lt;/a&gt; that I cherry picked from to structure my annual review, if you’re interested in doing your own. Highly recommend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I selected a few pieces of my review to expand upon for this post. Let’s dive in!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;main-section&quot;&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;2022-goal-review&quot;&gt;2022 Goal Review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2022, I set and tracked annual goals for the first time. I limited big goals to one or two, and added on a few easier ones. Despite not hitting all of them, they kept me very focused during my day-to-day, making me question whether what I was doing was necessary to help me achieve these goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;✅ &lt;strong&gt;Read 12 books.&lt;/strong&gt; I discovered audiobooks and blew this one out of the water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;✅ &lt;strong&gt;Re-read 2 books.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;✅ &lt;strong&gt;Launch personal blog.&lt;/strong&gt; We know how that turned out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;❌ &lt;strong&gt;Build an app that I or my friends use.&lt;/strong&gt; Overly ambitious given the state of my coding skillset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;❌ &lt;strong&gt;Launch a revenue-generating startup.&lt;/strong&gt; I’m coming to find that things take MUCH longer than expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;main-section&quot;&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;learning-through-experience&quot;&gt;Things I already knew, but “learned” through experience in 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you experience something for the first time, even if you already knew it existed, it can give you a newfound appreciation or understanding of it. Reflecting on my year through this lens was a fun exercise, so I plan to do it annually going forward. Here are my big ones from 2022:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;Burnout is real&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve always considered relentless energy and motivation to be one of my greatest strengths. People often talk about how motivation comes in waves, but I’ve been fortunate enough to never have experienced that. Until 2022, I can’t recall a time when my motivation ever really waned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it was a combination of launching a startup, working a full-time job, learning to code, and just being in my early thirties that caused me to experience burnout for the first time. Burnout was something I had heard about, but just assumed didn’t apply to me, so I never really thought about how to avoid or manage it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to express the feeling with words, but my tangible sense of motivation disappeared for a period during early 2022. Not ideal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is that it forced me to take a break and relax. Sure enough, my motivation returned after a few weeks, but the whole experience was unpleasant enough to teach me a few lessons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Trying to be productive all the time is counterproductive&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Breaks are incredibly important&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Accomplishing a little bit each day is more sustainable and effective in the long run than trying to chain together massively productive long hour workdays&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I plan to be more mindful of these in 2023 since I’m clearly not an invincible 20 year old anymore! (hopefully I look back on these days as being an invincible 30 year old 😎)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;Depression is real&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2022, I experienced depression for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to my early thirties, I had always been a consistently happy and energetic guy. Despite having a good life and a year full of many great experiences, a confluence of career and lifestyle factors sent me into a funk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For most of the year, I was consistently sad (or at least not happy) in the absence of any positive exogenous stressors, such as going on a trip, going out with friends, or visiting family. There were definitely more bad days than good ones in 2022, which was a shocking realization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, lots of great things happened last year, but the lows often hurt more than the highs feel good, and the intensity of depression still takes up a disproportionate amount of my memory of 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like burnout, I always knew that depression was a thing, but assumed it wouldn’t happen to me. Experience made me appreciate it for what it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finally started going to therapy (after MUCH persuasion from Sarah). It’s early days, but talking to someone who is just there to listen and react objectively seems to help, and I’m in a pretty good headspace going into 2023. Who woulda thunk!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;Sales is hard&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It is shockingly difficult to get people to part with their money.&lt;/strong&gt; I could have told you that a year ago, but in 2022, I experienced it firsthand trying to win early customers for my startup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve always thought of myself as a good salesperson since I have an innate ability to get other people excited about things, but 2022 was a reality check.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a pure sales context, with no company, brand, product or reputation behind you, the bar is so much higher. The atmosphere of the room shifts when it comes time for the prospect to actually part with their money, or even just agree to something. The creativity of excuses I received never ceased to amaze me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alas, a lesson in entrepreneurship being about getting people to take action (and having a high rejection tolerance!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;Hiring is hard&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After resigning from work, I was intimately involved in the process of hiring my replacement. This was much harder than I expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent the first decade of my career in finance, which involved many highly competitive interview processes. From where I was sitting back then, getting hired seemed to be the real challenge, while the companies seemed to have their pick of the lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was eye opening to experience the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;pressure&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; of finding the right candidate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a candidate, the consequences of not getting any individual job are inherently limited since you can always interview with another company. But hiring the wrong person can be value subtracting and have a big negative impact on your company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if you do get it wrong, the problem cannot be resolved quickly given the time it takes to conclude someone is not a good fit, run another search/interview process, and onboard the replacement. Searching for and interviewing candidates is a very considered process, and there is a lot of pressure to hire the right person. More than I anticipated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I could have told you this a year ago, but experiencing the higher stakes really hit it home for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A few additional takeaways:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The talent pool was worse than I expected.&lt;/strong&gt; My finance interview processes always felt super competitive, with no shortage of uber-qualified candidates, but sitting on the other side of the table, I was disappointed by the majority of candidates we saw. Regardless of whether it’s a buyer’s or seller’s labor market, it’s competitive on both sides of the table. Alas, another case of the grass being greener on the other side.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I used to think it was unfair to not receive feedback&lt;/strong&gt; on why I didn’t advance to the next round of interviews. I now understand that it’s nearly impossible to provide every candidate with feedback on why they didn’t move forward. This is due to both time constraints and passing on many candidates for something as simple as a poor case study submission early in the process. I still tried to pass along feedback to as many as I could.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hiring biases are real.&lt;/strong&gt; I was hiring for a client-facing role where excellent verbal and written English is critical. Non-native English speakers (or those without excellent English) are at a de facto disadvantage, regardless of how talented or hard-working they may be. This can come through during interviews and in written assessments, and it is unfortunately difficult to mentally adjust for.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;American Ninja Warrior is hard&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I visited Tel Aviv last summer, I stumbled upon a random ninja warrior park. I couldn’t resist and tried almost every obstacle. Impossible!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew it was hard, but experiencing it gave me new respect for those warriors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;main-section&quot;&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;best-books&quot;&gt;Best books I read in 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not part of my annual review, but I felt compelled to share these bangers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B09CCP2VWX/ref=x_gr_bb_kindle?caller=Goodreads&amp;amp;tag=x_gr_bb_kindle-20&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Burn Rate&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. This is a book about mental illness under the cover of the Bonobos origin story. I have a new appreciation for the implications of bipolar disorder. Easily the most fascinating book I read in 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Never-Split-Difference-Negotiating-Depended-ebook/dp/B014DUR7L2/ref=sr_1_1?crid=2PPJ2HCTPE287&amp;amp;keywords=never+split+the+difference&amp;amp;qid=1673415614&amp;amp;s=digital-text&amp;amp;sprefix=never+split+the+differ%2Cdigital-text%2C463&amp;amp;sr=1-1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Never Split The Difference&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Recommended to me by a good friend as the “best negotiating book he’s ever read”. While this is the only negotiating book I’ve read, it was excellent… to be referenced for years to come. Written by the former head of hostage negotiation for the FBI, it is full of high stakes stories of real life negotiations and is incredibly practical. “How am I supposed to do that?!” (if you know, you know)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/How-Music-Got-Free-Obsession-ebook/dp/B00OZ0TKL6/ref=sr_1_1?crid=2E1P5RG83PUME&amp;amp;keywords=how+music+got+free&amp;amp;qid=1673415571&amp;amp;s=digital-text&amp;amp;sprefix=how+music+got+fr%2Cdigital-text%2C435&amp;amp;sr=1-1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How Music Got Free&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. A detailed account of the digital piracy revolution of the late 1990s and 2000s. A fun trip down memory lane to my days using Kazaa and LimeWire in middle school. Spyware, anyone?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Who-Michael-Ovitz-ebook/dp/B07B2HS77M/ref=sr_1_1?crid=20SA29K9QVPYF&amp;amp;keywords=who+is+michael+ovitz&amp;amp;qid=1673415644&amp;amp;s=digital-text&amp;amp;sprefix=who+is+michael+ovitz%2Cdigital-text%2C396&amp;amp;sr=1-1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Who Is Michael Ovitz?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; The memoir of a Hollywood super-agent. Especially interesting if you’re into movies and entertainment.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Tokyo-Vice-American-Reporter-Vintage-ebook/dp/B002RYXA0Y/ref=sr_1_1?crid=1IBXGG4XTWLYQ&amp;amp;keywords=tokyo+vice&amp;amp;qid=1673415668&amp;amp;s=digital-text&amp;amp;sprefix=tokyo+vice%2Cdigital-text%2C414&amp;amp;sr=1-1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tokyo Vice&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Gripping tales from a American reporter covering the police beat in 1990s Japan. It’s an unbelievable story, and the author is an excellent storyteller. Be warned, it gets dark.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;main-section&quot;&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;2023-goal-setting&quot;&gt;2023 Goal Setting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working through my 2022 annual review inspired me to be even more deliberate about setting goals for 2023. Publishing them online seemed like a good way to hold myself accountable 💪.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried to set a few big goals that important to me and serve as milestones for achieving even bigger goals in the future. For each big goal, I also set a handful of “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sahilbloom.com/newsletter/the-annual-planning-guide&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;checkpoint goals&lt;/a&gt;” and put some systems in place to set myself up to hit them (e.g. 1 hour of coding, 4x per week). I also set some simple reading and writing goals just to keep me on course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here’s what I’m trying to nail in 2023:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;🎯 &lt;strong&gt;Write 6 blog posts.&lt;/strong&gt; 1 per quarter felt like too little, 1 per month felt like too much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;🎯 &lt;strong&gt;Read 13 new books.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;🎯 &lt;strong&gt;Re-read 2 books.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;🎯 &lt;strong&gt;Achieve full shoulder width body squat with heels on floor.&lt;/strong&gt; My ankle mobility sucks. This will set the foundation to achieve more advanced fitness goals down the road (see below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;🎯 &lt;strong&gt;Build an app that solves a problem for me.&lt;/strong&gt; I have a side project I’m working on. Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;🎯 &lt;strong&gt;Get 10 paying customers for my startup.&lt;/strong&gt; Big goal #1. 10 customers would represent proof-of-concept and significant revenue, but it’s not completely outlandish. This also sets me up to achieve big goal #2…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;🎯 &lt;strong&gt;Raise money for my startup.&lt;/strong&gt; Successfully raising in 2023 is a good barometer for our targeted level of growth and is required to scale into 2024 and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I piggy-backed off this annual goal-setting inspiration to set some &lt;strong&gt;longer term fitness goals&lt;/strong&gt; too. There is no deadline on these, just guiding North Stars for what I’m working towards long term:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Goal&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rationale&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;20 pull ups (dead hang)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Upper body strength&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Deadlift body weight 10 reps&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Total body strength&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-eOrqGTpv6o&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Nordic curl&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Posterior strength&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Hang from a bar - 2 min&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Grip strength&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Wall sit - 2 min&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Lower body strength&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qDcniqddTeE&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;pistol squat&lt;/a&gt; each leg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Lower body mobility&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pn8mqlG0nkE&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Overhead squat&lt;/a&gt; body weight 1 rep&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Total body strength/mobility&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5 min cycle w/watt output at 1.5x body weight&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Cardiovascular fitness&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Broad jump my height laying down&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Lower body strength&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Farmer’s carry body weight - 1 min&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Total body strength&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I anticipate these taking several years to achieve at a pace that will avoid injury. Off we go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;main-section&quot;&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;cool-thing&quot;&gt;A cool thing I discovered in 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought I’d leave you with this: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.futureme.org/letters/new&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Futureme&lt;/a&gt;. This website lets you send a letter to your future self (they email you the letter at a specified time in the future).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote a letter to myself in five years and one to myself in 10 years. I plan to write one to my 80 year old self as well. Pretty cool!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there it is. A little late getting this one out, but we did it. I hope you found something useful or inspiring in this post. Onward to discovering more cool things in 2023!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;thanks-text&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks to Sarah for reading a draft of this post.
&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">You must be at least [this] tall to ride this rollercoaster</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A lunatic’s guide to productivity</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/11/28/a-lunatics-guide-to-productivity.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A lunatic’s guide to productivity" /><published>2022-11-28T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-11-28T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/11/28/a-lunatics-guide-to-productivity</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/11/28/a-lunatics-guide-to-productivity.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;in-this-article&quot;&gt;In this article:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Productivity and what to work on&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#productivity-no-nos&quot;&gt;My productivity no-nos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#sustainable-productivity&quot;&gt;Sustainable productivity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#productivity-hacks&quot;&gt;Productivity hacks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#productivity-vices&quot;&gt;My productivity vices&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve spent a lot of time thinking about productivity. This is probably because I inherently hate wasting time, but partially because I’m taking a &lt;a href=&quot;https://eddymikes.me/2022/08/07/quitter.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;risky turn&lt;/a&gt; in life. Maximizing my productive output has become more important commensurate with the higher stakes I’ve set for myself. Spend two minutes scrolling through the Twittersphere, and it’s clear that productivity is a topic of general interest, so I felt inspired to consolidate my thinking around how I stay productive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before getting into the obligatory “hacks” list, it’s important to mention that all the productivity tips and tricks don’t really matter if you’re working on the wrong thing or are not genuinely interested in what you’re doing. Unless you’re superhuman, it’s nearly impossible to give it everything you’ve got when you’re working on something you don’t care about. Motivation is extremely sensitive to interest in both directions. Sam Altman expands on this &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.samaltman.com/productivity&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;well&lt;/a&gt;, so I won’t reinvent the wheel here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with two of my big &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;productivity no-nos&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;main-section&quot;&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;productivity-no-nos&quot;&gt;Productivity no-no #1: The Optimization Trap&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focusing so much on how to be more productive that it becomes counterproductive.&lt;/strong&gt; Essentially just over-optimizing. Productivity hacks are seductive, so this is a slippery slope. Admittedly, I’ve found myself here before, but I try to be self-aware about whether I’m falling into the trap in real time. The majority of productivity hacks offer only marginal benefits, and sometimes you just need to get going on whatever it is you’re working on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;main-section&quot;&gt;Productivity no-no #2: The Grind Trap&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blindly focusing on “efficiency” and number of tasks completed.&lt;/strong&gt; I call it the “&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;grind trap&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;”. Productivity is not just about efficiency, it’s about impact. You can use energy efficiently to run on a treadmill, it doesn’t mean you’re going anywhere. It sounds obvious, but it’s an easy trap to fall into mainly because grinding out tasks tends to be less cognitively demanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spending all morning advancing slightly on a super impactful project is often more productive in the long run than cranking out a bunch of to-do list items. But smashing through your to-do list feels good and is usually easier. Don’t get me wrong, there will always be times to just sit down and bang stuff out, but generally speaking, measuring your productivity by number of tasks completed without thinking about their impact on your medium-to-long term goals is not value maximizing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re really “productive” at doing things that shouldn’t be your first priority, you aren’t really being productive, and the opportunity cost is high! A little bit of time spent on something each day grows into an enormous amount of time spent on it in the long run (see “day compounding” below). So consistently getting caught in the grind trap can magnify into massive productivity losses over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I try to avoid the grind trap by constantly asking myself whether I’m actually being productive or just “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/4-Hour-Workweek-Escape-Live-Anywhere/dp/0307465357&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;active&lt;/a&gt;” (I even set up a little reminder post-it note that stares me in the face all day). A good mental model for this is the “run up-hill” framework, which says that when torn between two paths, it usually pays to choose the one that’s more difficult in the short term. On balance, the more intellectually demanding tasks tend to be the more impactful ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to do, but just remember, we humans are momentum fiends: force yourself to take that difficult first step, and every one after that becomes significantly easier. This blog post is a great example. I’ve been putting it off for days because it was easier to jam through other less demanding tasks on my list!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;main-section&quot;&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;sustainable-productivity&quot;&gt;Day compounding and sustainable productivity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has never been more in-vogue to talk about compounding. I hate to follow the crowd here, but it’s true. Not just financial compounding, but the compounding effects of how you spend your time. This works to your advantage in almost every area of life, from fitness and relationships to learning and productivity. If you can gain one more productive hour per workday, in a year, that’s 260 hours. In five, that’s 1,300 hours. The long term impact of small but consistent productivity gains is massive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generating productivity gains that compound is only possible if your methods are sustainable. I’ve found the easiest way to do this is to seek methods with a high &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;impact-to-ease of implementation ratio&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. Whatever you do to be more productive, it should be relatively easy to implement and keep doing, and it should have an outsized positive impact on your productivity. Like with anything in life, finding these involves a lot of trial and error, and there may be some minor productivity losses in the pursuit of productivity gains. Everybody has different things that work for them, so don’t be afraid to give something a shot even if it doesn’t seem suitable to you at first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve tried a lot of methods over the years and have come up with a pretty reliable list that works for me. As promised, this wouldn’t be an article on productivity without a “hacks” list, so without further ado…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;main-section&quot;&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;productivity-hacks&quot;&gt;Things that had a significant impact on my productivity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;thanks-text&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Quick disclaimer: It’s important to maintain some degree of flexibility in your workflow. I try to do a lot of these things as regularly as possible, but life comes at ya. Being arbitrarily rigid is counterproductive.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;⚡ Setting a daily to-do list the night before&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cannot promote this one enough. I understand how this could seem trivial, what’s wrong with setting your daily to-do list first thing in the morning? The answer: a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setting your daily to-do list involves choosing from a larger list of to-dos, then prioritizing. We’re not talking rocket science here, but this is an important and somewhat thoughtful exercise. Setting your daily to-do list first thing in the morning means the first thing you do is spend time &lt;em&gt;contemplating and making a decision&lt;/em&gt;. Setting your daily to-do list the night before means the first thing you do is &lt;em&gt;take action&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to spend my peak mental hours immediately diving into meaningful work that requires high impact decision making, not making a decision about how to spend my day. Setting your daily to-do list the night before lets you avoid a small, but momentum-sucking decision and allows you to start your day by immediately executing on what you’ve already decided upon doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember how humans are momentum fiends? This one falls in the category of “getting out of your own way” by kickstarting the momentum train. Same deal with laying out your gym clothes the night before, so you can just roll out of bed, put them on, and head straight to the gym. Do yourself a favor!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My daily to-do list for this past weekend looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/notion-daily-to-do-list.png&quot; alt=&quot;notion-daily-to-do-list&quot; title=&quot;notion-to-do-list&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rarely does anything ever make it onto the “mission critical” list. If something is truly mission critical, I will literally not do anything else until that thing is complete. Most things aren’t mission critical by this definition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I try to limit the “top priority” list to a maximum of two items. These tend to be more cognitively demanding and impactful tasks, but don’t have to be. My criteria for something to be “top priority” are urgency and impact. The “if possible” bucket is for less urgent things that are still relatively important in the near term. This to-do list structure is essentially my own version of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Time_management#The_Eisenhower_Method&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Eisenhower Matrix&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This exercise is usually the last thing I do before “signing off” of work for the evening. I do it most days, and once before the weekend if I have some stuff to get done. If I’m caught up on things or not particularly busy, I’ll skip it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;⚡ Getting up super early&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting up early has two main benefits for me: 1) it maximizes distraction-free peak mental hours, and 2) it minimizes “time slippage”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My peak mental hours are between waking up and lunch time, and everything after that is a steady decline. The world comes online around 8-9am, and distractions start to roll in. Waking up earlier shifts more of my peak mental time into the distraction-free zone. The productivity benefits are self-evident.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t until I started regularly waking up early that I realized &lt;strong&gt;time slippage is EVERYWHERE&lt;/strong&gt;. I define time slippage as the difference in time required to do something if it’s done early versus later in the morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are just a few annoying examples of things that take longer if done later in the morning with some conservative time loss estimates:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The gym is more crowded (lose ~10 minutes)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The elevator is more crowded and makes more stops (lose ~3 minutes, depending on the size of your building)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There’s more traffic, or the subway is slower/more crowded (lose ~10 minutes)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are other dogs on the street distracting my dog from peeing so the walk takes longer (lose ~10 minutes)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These four examples alone would cost me ~30 minutes a day of my most mentally productive time. That’s more than a workday per month that I can get back just by waking up earlier! Of course this isn’t exact math, and everyone’s routine is different, but it’s directionally true: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;waking up early literally buys you time&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the gains compound: an hour at 6am is worth much more to me than an hour at 10am.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond the distraction-free time and minimized time slippage, there’s also the motivation derived from knowing you’re crushing the day. It’s cringy but true. Don’t knock it ‘til you try it 😉&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m generally in bed around 9pm and wake up at 5am, snoozing to between 5:10 and 5:20 (though sometimes much longer). I tried pulling a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bob_Iger&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Bob Iger&lt;/a&gt; and waking up at 4:45am, but I couldn’t swing it. He’s a machine!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;thanks-text&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;One caveat: I fully acknowledge that I am a morning person through and through. Some people aren’t and do their best work late into the night. Waking up early isn’t for everyone. It’s more important to structure your workday around your peak mental hours rather than arbitrarily waking up early simply because it&apos;s associated with being productive.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;⚡ Adopting &lt;a href=&quot;https://affiliate.notion.so/8moig6rseq6t&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Notion&lt;/a&gt; to organize my life&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a BIG one. I’m constantly surprised by the number of people who haven’t heard of Notion, despite it being a massively successful software startup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notion is a cloud-based documents app, super charged with useful functionality, wrapped into a simple and customizable folder structure&lt;/strong&gt;. What Notion does for my level of organization makes me constantly think “where have you been all my life?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notion can be used for &lt;em&gt;almost&lt;/em&gt; anything, but here are a few personal examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;no-bullet-list&quot;&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;☑️ To-do lists&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;☑️ Any other kind of list&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;☑️ All note-taking (forget Evernote)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;☑️ Writing, collaborating on, and sharing documents&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;☑️ Event planning / guest list tracking&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;☑️ Project management&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;☑️ Travel planning&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;☑️ Saving articles&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;☑️ Recording workouts&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;☑️ Drafting blog posts 😉&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this stuff is simply organized into one place, with a bunch of embedded functionality. &lt;strong&gt;It’s like outsourcing part of your brain.&lt;/strong&gt; Notion is one of those things that’s so simple and works so well, that you can’t help but ask yourself: “how did this not exist 10 years ago?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and there’s a great mobile app, so all of your stuff is at your fingertips on the go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting a Notion account can be a little intimidating. The application is infinitely flexible, and all the functionality choices can be a bit overwhelming. There’s also no shortage of YouTube gurus out there promoting the most optimized and sexy personal dashboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t worry about all that. Start small, and see if it’s for you. Some people prefer a good ol’ handwritten to-do list, and that’s fine too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an effort to not be completely biased, here are the only things I’ve found that Notion is not great for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;no-bullet-list&quot;&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;❌ Anything that’s done best in Excel (don’t come at the King!)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;❌ Cloud file storage&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;❌ Calendar functionality (although they plan to integrate with Google Calendar)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;⚡ Ignoring email&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hot take alert! This one is both critical and controversial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The level of focus you will achieve by ignoring email entirely for three hours at a time is hard to understate. Email is an attention stealer, and most emails do not require an urgent response (I’m sure there are some fields where this isn’t the case, but I’ll venture to guess there are few). And yet, we’re carpet bombed with these little things all day long, constantly breaking our focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;quote-block&quot;&gt;“But wait! How can you ignore email?!
What if someone needs to get in touch with you?!
Aren’t you negatively impacting your teammates’ productivity?!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No. I solve for this in three ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make sure the relevant people know how to contact you for urgent matters. Either via text, call, internal/external company chat, etc. Don’t be off grid, just don’t be constantly breaking focus to check your inbox.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Understand that if something is truly urgent, the person will find a way to get in touch with you. If you’re contactable, but they can’t figure out how to reach you, it’s not urgent enough.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Skim your email three times a day for urgent messages only, then block off 30 minutes to one hour once per day to go through your entire inbox.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some days tend to be more email-heavy, and it’s hard to avoid, but I try to systematically skim and ignore email as often as I can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;main-section&quot;&gt;Other little productivity hacks&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;⚡ Drinking less&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one should be obvious. It’s amazing how many things in life fall into place when you cut down on alcohol. Energy, focus, cleanliness. The list is endless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;⚡ Uncomfortably cold showers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there’s one thing that gets rid of brain fog in the morning better than anything else, it’s a freezing &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pq6WHJzOkno&amp;amp;t=2093s&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;cold shower&lt;/a&gt;. The water should be so cold you can barely tolerate it, then stand in it for two full minutes (set a timer). Never has two minutes felt so much like an eternity!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I admit, it’s miserable, but the benefits are real for me. I get out of the shower extremely energized, and the mental clarity often lasts for hours. I only do this once or so per week since it’s so unpleasant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;⚡ Switching from coffee to green tea&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find the peaks and troughs of coffee’s caffeine buzz to be relatively extreme, and they always have me coming back to the machine for another espresso. By the early afternoon, I’ve already had two or three espressos, and I’m entering “more coffee will disrupt my sleep” territory. I end up forced into this groggy state in need of more caffeine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter green tea. I find that green tea’s caffeine buzz is longer lasting than coffee’s, with less pronounced peaks and troughs. I don’t get jittery, and the crash is more of a “soft landing”, allowing me to stay focused for longer. I also end up consuming less caffeine overall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll usually have a cup in the early morning, maybe another in the late morning, then one after lunch if necessary. I also love matcha. Throw a little almond milk and turmeric in there, pro tip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not religious about this and will have a coffee here and there since I love the taste so much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;⚡ Intermittent fasting and low carb lunches&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intermittent fasting (”IF”) is widely promoted on the health and fitness circuit these days. For me, IF just entails eating an early dinner and skipping breakfast a few times per week. This creates a fasting window of around 14 to 16 hours, which is commonly referred to as the 16-8 fasting method (16 hours of fasting, 8 hours to eat your meals).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there are alleged &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9tRohh0gErM&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;health and longevity benefits&lt;/a&gt;, I’m not promoting those. I do it for two productivity-related reasons: 1) I don’t have to think about making and eating breakfast, and 2) I feel better and am more focused for longer through lunchtime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming I’ve gotten a good night’s sleep, my mental acuity is higher, and my morning energy is more consistent when I’m fasting. I try to extend this by keeping weekday lunches very low in carbs to avoid the afternoon crash. It works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: If you get so hungry that you can’t think straight, this defeats the purpose, and you should just eat. I also don’t fast after big strength training workouts. Read up on the risks of fasting before you try it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;⚡ Stop reading the news&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The news is a doom-scrollable list of headlines and stories jockeying for your eyeballs, 99% of which do not matter to your life (this excludes careers that require following certain news very closely).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re worried about not knowing what’s going on in the world, don’t be. If something is important enough, unless you are a bona fide recluse, there is a 100% chance you will hear about it, and hearing about it first matters zero. If your goal is to be “informed” and sound smart, read books or long form deep dives on topics you’re interested in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I subscribe to a few newsletters that blast out a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.execsum.co/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;list&lt;/a&gt; of the top headlines, and I’ll take a minute to skim through that. If something really important or interesting happened, I’ll dig into it further, but this is rare. I used to spend 30 minutes to an hour a day doom-scrolling through the news, the majority of which I didn’t retain. Waste of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;⚡ Building in time to screw around and do nothing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is less of a hack, and more something I think is simply necessary. Burnout is real, and if you’re trying to be productive all the time, this will quickly work against you. I’ve been there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re human beings with a finite capacity for mentally demanding work each day. If you spend too much time draining your mental gas tank for too long, your overall level of cognitive performance and motivation will suffer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t be afraid to relax. Working hard is important, but slipping into “hustle culture” is counterproductive in the long run. Build in time to hang with friends, spend time outside, or sit around and watch TV to let your brain reset, like taking a rest day after a workout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;main-section&quot;&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;productivity-vices&quot;&gt;My productivity vices&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some people it’s procrastination, for others it’s chocolate. For me, it’s YouTube, Twitter, and the snooze button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;🐌 YouTube&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I LOVE YouTube. It’s longer form and is usually more informational than Instagram, but still bite-sized enough to use during a short break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I had a nickel for every time I cracked open a video with the intention of watching one or two, but found myself an hour later down some unexpected rabbit hole…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;🐌 Twitter&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one can be scary since it’s “intellectual” and doom-scrollable. A dangerous cocktail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s hard not to keep scrolling after you open it, and there’s so much garbage interspersed throughout the good content that Twitter scrolls can be pretty mindless if you’re not selective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I request to see less of certain people or topics regularly (akin to “unsubscribing”), but I still find Twitter scrolls sucking up an unnecessary amount of my time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sub-section&quot;&gt;🐌 Snooze button&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is less of a vice and more of an Achilles Heel. In bad cases, I’ve been known to snooze in 15 minute increments for up to two hours. Brutal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of how well-rested I am, I’m fully addicted to hitting snooze. All will power evaporates in the critical moment, and it costs me in time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If anyone knows how to conquer this one let me know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I had to ruthlessly narrow it down and leave you with three things to take away from this post: &lt;strong&gt;use &lt;a href=&quot;https://affiliate.notion.so/8moig6rseq6t&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Notion&lt;/a&gt;, wake up early, and set your to-do list the night before&lt;/strong&gt;. Drinking less gets an honorable mention 😂.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But hey, that’s just me. I’m always open to trying out the latest magic hack, so hit me up if you think you’ve found the secret sauce!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;thanks-text&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks to Sarah for reading a draft of this post.
&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Check me into the looney bin</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Quitter</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/08/07/quitter.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Quitter" /><published>2022-08-07T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-08-07T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/08/07/quitter</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/08/07/quitter.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve done it. I quit my job. Cue the “what have I done!?” tsunami.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just joking. This wasn’t a rash decision. In fact, it’s something I’ve been thinking deeply about for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m 31 with 9 years of experience in finance. Things have been going smoothly, or at least they appear to be from the outside looking in, but the recent reality has been an internal struggle as I face a growing dissatisfaction with my career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initial allure of working in finance wore off after my first few years, and the dissatisfaction started creeping its way in, ultimately morphing into full blown unhappiness over the last 2-3 years. After a hell of a lot of introspection, I’ve come to be much more critical of my choices and my career, and I have more clarity than ever before about what’s important to me in life. This all culminated in the decision to leave finance and go it alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To tell this story, let me run it back to ancient days of 2012…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started my career in investment banking for a few reasons. I don’t know if they were the right ones, they probably weren’t:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I wanted to learn a lot (about anything, just a lot)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I wanted to “credentialize” my CV&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Money&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My friends were doing it, and I identified with the culture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three out of four reasons revolve around one theme: preserving optionality. Knowing nothing about finance and having no idea what I wanted to do in life, that rationale seemed somewhat sensible, so I dove in. Almost a decade later, it’s clear that I wasn’t being intellectually honest about who I am, where my true interests lie, and what I (maybe) should be doing with my life… stubbornly “preserving optionality” at all costs without thinking critically about these things. I can chalk it up to immaturity, lack of experience, or just not knowing until I know, but here we are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back on the last 9 years moving through various sub-sectors of finance, two things occurred to me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I was never organically excited about what I was doing.&lt;/strong&gt; Every manifesto will tell you requirement #1 for being happy and successful in life is to love what you do. Ask anyone who knows me - I am an &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; enthusiastic person by nature. This never came through in my work. Big red flag🚩&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My absolutely highest performing state occurred when I was out of a job and out there hustling&lt;/strong&gt; to get hired by companies that felt out of my reach (in one case after already having left my job). My cognition and drive were on another level. I’ve worked on a handful of side hustles over the years and noticed the same thing. Something about the personal risk, upside, and lack of a salary safety net combined with pure organic interest unlocked something within me. This isn’t all that surprising, but sometimes it just hits home after the fact.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These realizations took me deeper down the introspection rabbit hole: How can I better spend my time to maximize my happiness and realize my full potential? What do I even like? What do I even want in life?!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Long story short, I distilled it down to this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Freedom.&lt;/strong&gt; Not being a slave to my job. Living the lifestyle I want. Living in a state of pure meritocracy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The ability to travel, live a comfortable healthy life, and have a big family.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Doing something impactful.&lt;/strong&gt; Having some sort of direct positive impact on other people or the world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what am I good at? More importantly, what am I good at that is relatively unique?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an effort to prevent this post from becoming one big pat on the back, I’ll leave it here: I energize others, I can &lt;a href=&quot;http://paulgraham.com/schlep.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;schlep&lt;/a&gt; like the best of them, and I’m decisive (I can “pull trig”, for better or worse).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then it dawned on me one day. I have been gravitating directly towards entrepreneurship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growing up, I watched my dad run his own business, and I had in the back of my mind that I’d also work for myself one day. Unfortunately, I did not think that deeply about how to realize that future back then, and the underlying desire to build something of my own was eventually diluted by the distractions of college and the allure of finance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just assumed this would be my future. I never allowed myself to recognize that taking action was not only within my power, but a requirement. It only took a decade of experience and deep reflection to trigger that line of thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m working on a startup in Hong Kong, and we have a stable product getting positive early feedback from customers. But we haven’t found product market fit and are not cash flow positive (although we have a modest burn rate). Some may say I’m derisked enough to take the leap, others may say I’m not even close. This is where risk tolerance becomes a matter of perspective. But regardless, even if this project wasn’t getting traction and I didn’t see a path to profitability, I’d quit my job anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recognize the importance of derisking decisions, but I also believe in the importance of leaning into your strengths and positioning yourself to get lucky. I’m not advocating that people recklessly hang their hat on getting lucky without a plan. That’s akin to gambling. I’m highlighting the importance of putting yourself on the right side of luck relative to your current position, within the limits of calculated risk taking. Consider your current position versus the position you’ll put yourself in and what that will do to your chances of success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not superhuman and am pretty incapable of delivering the required level of focus when my peak mental hours are consumed by a day job. It’s also the leap itself that pushes me to my maximum productive output, so in my case, maintaining the status quo is anything but positioning myself to get lucky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I’m well-positioned to succeed, and there are things I can do to further nudge the odds in my favor, including building passive income and maximizing my “at bats” through many small, controlled bets, but at the end of the day, I genuinely believe in myself enough to take the leap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, that’s where we are. After all that fancy introspection, it pretty much comes down to a good old entrepreneurial itch. And some itches must be scratched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you gotta burn the boats and bet on yourself. Away we go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;thanks-text&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks to Sarah for reading a draft of this post.
&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Jump!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why I started this blog</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/08/06/why-i-started-this-blog.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why I started this blog" /><published>2022-08-06T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-08-06T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/08/06/why-i-started-this-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/08/06/why-i-started-this-blog.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been thinking about starting a blog for a while, but here I am sitting at Hong Kong International Airport with two hours until my flight to New York, and something just came over me, so I started typing away. Here goes nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started this blog for three reasons: &lt;strong&gt;1) clear writing = clear thinking, 2) exploring unknown unknowns, and 3) accountability.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;main-section&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clear writing = clear thinking&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spend the vast majority of my intellectually demanding time consuming information and content, rather than producing/creating it. Books, podcasts, blogs, articles, my Twitter feed, YouTube videos… it’s pretty much a one way street of information input. That information represents the building blocks of my ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Translating ideas from thoughts into comprehendible written words challenges us to more deeply understand what we think. It’s amazing how I’ll think I know something and try to write it out, and that exercise reveals how hollow that thinking can be. There are other areas of life where I write - occasionally at my day job, for startups/side projects I’ve worked on, job hunts, and so on, but it’s pretty infrequent. Forcing myself to write more stimulates another part of my brain, reinforces and challenges my ideas, and improves the depth and quality of my thinking (if I was on the fence about that before, writing this first post proves it to me).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog is a pursuit of clearer, deeper thinking about the things that interest me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a rough idea of what I plan to write about (entrepreneurship/business, health &amp;amp; fitness, learning, productivity, travel/living abroad, anything else I come to be interested in), but I’m excited to see where this goes. Which brings me to my next reason…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;main-section&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exploring unknown unknowns&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideas beget ideas. I don’t understand the brain chemistry behind this, they just do. I don’t know what I’ll uncover or what ideas will occur to me by challenging myself to write more, but I know I’ll uncover something. It would be cool to see what that’s all about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;main-section&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accountability&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could just write in a journal, but there’s something about the act of posting online for the world to see. We’re not talking about high stakes here, but it does hold me to a higher standard. The internet is &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;forever&lt;/a&gt;, so there’s an incentive to really think through what I’m writing about… clear writing = clear thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those are the main reasons, but this is also another fun coding challenge! I’m picking up programming on the side, and a personal blog or website is a great early practical application of that skillset. This blog is completely self-developed and hosted using GitHub Pages, Jekyll, basic HTML/CSS, and Namecheap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an aside, despite having read it for some time, I only just noticed that a high school friend of mine has been running his &lt;a href=&quot;https://blas.com/essays/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;awesome blog&lt;/a&gt; for what appears to be the exact same reasons! One inspiration point to you, my friend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;main-section&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What’s in a name?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“E Mikes”, “Eddy Mikes” or many variations thereof was given to me as a nickname in high school, and it’s stuck ever since. Keepin’ it rolling!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
And BOOM! First blog post complete. Stay tuned for more, I hope you enjoy reading!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;thanks-text&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks to Sarah for reading a draft of this post.
&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Brain stuff</summary></entry></feed>